{"tossups": [{"question": "This city was built as part of a program that promised \u201cfifty years\u2019 progress in five.\u201d The state of Guanabara was made obsolete by this city\u2019s construction. A cathedral intended to be shaped like a crown of thorns was built in this city, which was built to resemble an airplane on a site in Goias state. Juscelino Kubitschek commissioned the building of, for the point, what planned city that was built to replace Rio de Janeiro as Brazil\u2019s capital?", "answer": "<b> Brasilia</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In his early career, this composer used Psalm 22 as the basis for his work \u201cthe Miserable Shall Eat,\u201dwhich was composed for the Leipzig city council. This composer was asked to alter a theme composed by Frederick the Great and did so in the \u201cMusical Offering.\u201d This man was commissioned by Keyserling, the count of Saxony, to compose a series of works to ease the count\u2019s insomnia. For the point, name this German Baroque composer of the Goldberg Variations and the Brandenburg Concertos.", "answer": "Johann Sebastian<b> Bach</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "One leader of this country created the \u201cGuulwaade\u201d cult of personality; that leader of this country effectively switched sides in the Cold War after the Soviet Union failed to support his invasion of a neighboring country in the Ogaden War. This country, which was once led by Siad Barre, was the site of the 1992 \u201cBlack Hawk Down\u201d incident. For the point, name this African country where warlords briefly captured the capital of Mogadishu.", "answer": "<b> Somalia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Varian Fry led efforts to rescue artists from this regime, which committed the Vel d\u2019Hiv [vell deev] massacre. A fleet was attacked at Mers el-Kebir to prevent it from falling into this regime\u2019s hands. A motto translating as \u201cWork, family, fatherland\u201d was used by this regime, which was founded at a town formerly best known as a resort. Pierre Laval was prime minister of, for the point, what regime led by the former commander of French forces in World War I, Philippe Petain, that collaborated with the Nazis?", "answer": "<b> Vichy</b> [vee-shee] France (accept the<b> French State</b>; accept<b> Etat Francais</b>; prompt on France and descriptions of Nazi-controlled France, including \u201cthe Nazis\u201d alone; do not accept (Nazi) Germany)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "After this event, the USS<em> Kirk</em> escorted hundreds of ships to Subic Bay. The most famous photograph by Hugh Van Es was taken during this event. Ambassador Graham Martin helped coordinate this event, which began with the signal of \u201cWhite Christmas\u201d being played on the radio on April 30, 1975. Operation Frequent Wind was the codename of, for the point, what event in which US forces and civilians withdrew from the capital of South Vietnam?", "answer": "US and/or South Vietnamese<b> evacuation of Saigon</b> (accept equivalents related to the<b> fall of Saigon</b>; accept Operation<b> Frequent Wind</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This artist painted<em> The Shelton with Sunspots</em> and chronicled a 1928 view of the<em> East River from the</em> <em>Thirtieth Story of the Shelton Hotel</em>, which was then the tallest hotel in the world. This creator of<em> Radiator</em> <em>Building</em> painted landscapes of the \u201cWhite Place\u201d in New Mexico, where she moved shortly before the death of her husband, photographer Alfred Stieglitz. For the point, name this American painter of<em> Cow\u2019s</em> <em>Skull: Red, White, and Blue</em> and many intimate close-ups of flowers.", "answer": "Georgia Totto<b> O\u2019Keeffe</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Photography"}, {}, {"question": "In a bloody engagement during this war, forces under George Drummond defeated Jacob Brown and Winfield Scott at the Battle of Lundy\u2019s Lane. After forces under Robert Ross were victorious in this war\u2019s Battle of Bladensburg, they proceeded to set fires in the capital that a tornado legendarily put out. The most memorable American victory occurred after this war at the Battle of New Orleans. For the point name this \u201csecond war of independence\u201d between the US and Britain, which began in a namesake year.", "answer": "War of<b> 1812</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This author reworked the myth of Orpheus for the 20th century rock music scene in a novel about Ormus Cara,<em> The Ground Beneath Her Feet</em>. The sister of another of this author\u2019s protagonists is a singer nicknamed \u201cthe brass monkey.\u201d Saladin Chamcha survives a plane crash in a novel that earned this author a death sentence in a<em> fatwa</em> from Ayatollah Khomeini. For the point, name this author of<em> The Satanic</em> <em>Verses</em> and<em> Midnight\u2019s Children</em>.", "answer": "Salman<b> Rushdie</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "anthippus [zanth-ip-us] was victorious at the Battle of Mycale [MI-kuh-lee]. This ruler\u2019s mother dreamed of giving birth to a lion before he was born. This man ostracized his political opponent Cimon and transported the treasury of the Delian League to his own city. For the point, name this Athenian statesman, who delivered a famous funeral oration during the Peloponnesian War.", "answer": "<b> Pericles</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This politician, who referred to the United States as a \u201ctower of freedom\u201d in a campaign speech, was mentored by wealthy newspaper publisher Thurlow Weed. During his tenure as Governor of New York, this man prosecuted Alexander McLeod for his involvement in the<em> Caroline</em> Affair. This man survived an assassination attempt by Lewis Powell on April 14, 1865. For the point, name this Secretary of State under Abraham Lincoln and Andrew Johnson who orchestrated the purchase of Alaska.", "answer": "William Henry<b> Seward</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This ethnic group fought the largely violence-free Dog Tax War against the British. This ethnic group signed a treaty that was originally drafted by James Busby and translated poorly by Henry Williams. George Grey fought a leader of these peoples named Hono Heke [hay-kay] after a flagpole was cut down. After Europeans made contact with these people, they fought the Moriori people on the Chatham Islands during the Musket Wars. William Hobson compelled this indigenous group to sign the Treaty of Waitangi. For the point, name this native ethnic group of New Zealand.", "answer": "<b> Maori</b> people (prompt on descriptions of indigenous New Zealanders before \u201cNew Zealand\u201dis read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s rejection of a humiliating peace treaty with Nazi Germany is celebrated on its \u201cNo Day.\u201d This country, which was ruled by the Regime of the Colonels, was the westernmost of the first two countries to receive aid under the Truman Doctrine. The fascist regime of Ioannis Metaxas ruled this country before World War II, and the Enosis movement aimed to unify Cyprus with this country. For the point, name this country in which German paratroopers successfully captured the island of Crete.", "answer": "<b> Greece</b> (accept<b> Hellenic Republic</b>; accept<b> Hellas</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Robert Bellarmine prominently cracked down on people who held this belief, which Francesco Ingoli attacked with eighteen objections in a notable letter. An advocate of this belief was ardently opposed by Tycho Brahe and legendarily declared \u201cand yet it moves\u201d while being arrested. The European originator of this view started a namesake \u201cRevolution\u201d that shattered the Ptolemaic model. Galileo and Copernicus held, for the point, what scientific theory that opposed geocentrism?", "answer": "<b> heliocentrism</b> (accept descriptions of \u201cthe<b> Sun</b> is at the<b> center</b> of the<b> solar system and/or universe</b>\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the aftermath of this event, Anne Vaux was arrested and accused of harboring conspirators in her house. Henry Garnet was executed for his role in this event, which he knew about through information revealed in the confessional. Robert Catesby led the conspirators in this event, which was foiled after Guy Fawkes was discovered guarding barrels of explosives in a basement. For the point, name this event in which Catholics plotted to destroy the Houses of Parliament in 1605.", "answer": "<b> Gunpowder</b> Plot", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "After the first Sino-Japanese War, China was forced to recognize the independence of this region in the Treaty of Shimonoseki. Japan forced this region to become its protectorate with the Eulsa Treaty, and a member of this region\u2019s \u201cpatriotic legion\u201d attempted to assassinate Emperor Showa. Toyotomi Hideyoshi attempted to invade this region, but failed due to Admiral Yi Sun-sin. For the point, name this peninsula that was annexed by Japan in 1910 and contains the cities of Pyongyang and Seoul.", "answer": "<b> Korea</b>n Peninsula (do not accept North Korea or South Korea)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "France attempted to establish plantations for this good in the Niger Bend after Britain successfully did so in Sudan\u2019s Gezira Triangle. A crash in prices for this good led Egypt\u2019s debt to skyrocket in the 1860s, thus leading to a British protectorate over it. Irrigation for this good drained most of the Aral Sea in Uzbekistan, and a machine for processing this good was invented in America by Eli Whitney. For the point, name this trade good nicknamed \u201cKing\u201d in the antebellum US south.", "answer": "<b> cotton</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "For the point, name this mountain range that stretches along much of the eastern US.", "answer": "<b> Appalachian</b> Mountains (accept Great<b> Smoky</b> Mountains, or Great<b> Smokies</b>, until \u201cBlack Mountains\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "As a child, this man had a \u201ctoy army\u201d consisting of playmates who eventually became the core of his Imperial Guard. After capturing Azov, this leader built his country\u2019s first naval base at Taganrog. This ruler put down a Cossack revolt sparked by bounty-hunting of fugitive serfs led by Kondraty Bulavin. This monarch\u2019s reforms included a promotion system called the Table of Ranks and a beard tax. For the point, name this Tsar who westernized Russia at the start of the 18th century.", "answer": "<b> Peter the Great</b> (or<b> Peter I</b>; prompt on Peter)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In a meeting responding to this action, Bob McNair controversially complained that they \u201ccan\u2019t have inmates running the prison.\u201d In 2017, after the College of the Ozarks announced a new policy responding to this action, the NAIA moved a men\u2019s basketball championship game out of Branson. A meeting with former Green Beret Nate Boyer inspired this action, which has led to a collusion grievance due to the unusual lack of interest in a free agent quarterback. For the point, name this ongoing form of protest that was started in 2016 by Colin Kaepernick [cap-er-nick].", "answer": "<b> kneeling</b> during the<b> National Anthem</b> (accept descriptive answers that mention both parts, such as \u201c<b>kneeling</b> for the<b> Star-Spangled Banner</b>; prompt on partial answers, like \u201cprotesting the anthem\u201d and \u201ckneeling\u201d alone)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "During one battle, this warrior told the attacking side \u201cBegone, or I will make you go\u201d days before urging an attack on the bastille of St. Laurent. This soldier convinced Dauphin Charles to launch the March to Reims [rahnse], allowing his coronation as king. Because heresy only carried a death penalty if it was a repeat offense, an English court charged this woman with cross-dressing. For the point, name this\u201cMaid of Orleans\u201d who was burned at the stake during the Hundred Years\u2019 War.", "answer": "Saint<b> Joan</b> of Arc (accept<b> Jeanne</b> d\u2019Arc)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man purchased a newspaper operation from Samuel Keimer and founded a debate club known as the Junto. This man, whose son was the last Royalist Governor of New Jersey, used the pseudonym Richard Saunders to detail weather forecasts in colonial America and created a political cartoon depicting a snake cut into eight segments.<em> Join, or Die</em> was created by, for the point, what Pennsylvanian Founding Father and publisher of<em> Poor Richard\u2019s Almanac</em>?", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Franklin</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A combatant in this war, Shiro Ishii, was controversially given amnesty in exchange for his scientific data. A combatant in this war, Hiroo Onoda, remained at his post for 27 years after it ended. The Japanese army enslaved Koreans as \u201ccomfort women\u201d during this war, in which Japan fought a united front of Chinese Communists and Nationalists. For the point, name this war in which Japan surrendered after being attacked with two nuclear weapons.", "answer": "<b> W</b>orld<b> W</b>ar<b> II</b> (accept<b> Second Sino-Japanese</b> War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Workers at a company in this industry were first allowed to talk during lunch after a 1937 sit down strike that included intervention by John L. Lewis. Walter Reuther led a union in this industry, which fought security forces at the Battle of the Overpass. One company in this industry was owned by a man who ran the anti-Semitic newspaper<em> Dearborn Independent</em>. Conditions in this industry were improved by the Treaty of Detroit. For the point, name this American industry that includes companies like Chrysler and Ford.", "answer": "<b> auto</b>mobile industry (accept anything related to the production and/or sales of<b> car</b>s, etc.) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country\u2019s founding fathers are known as the thirty-three Orientals, a reference to its colonial name, Banda Oriental. Like Brazil and Italy, this country underwent a civil war in which Giuseppe Garibaldi took part. A civil war between this country\u2019s Colorados and Blancos was the cause of the War of the Triple Alliance. For the point, name this country where political factions frequently clashed in the capital of Montevideo.", "answer": "<b> Uruguay</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}